# **SANDY JAN E. LABAROSA**

Drussustraße 10, Bonn 53111, Germany

Mobile: +49 176 29205379

Email: sandyjanlabarosa@gmail.com

Personal website: https://www.pgradvocate.com

I am an advocate for plant genetic resources for food and agriculture conservation, management, and sustainable use and development, with two years experience in the field of rice breeding research and two years in agricultural community development in Southeast Asia. I am interested in plant breeding and crop-wild relatives research.

#### **EDUCATION**

# Master of Science in Agricultural Sciences and Resource Management in the Tropics and Subtropics (ARTS)

Oct 2019 – Sept 2021

Rheinische Friedrich-Wilhems-Universität Bonn, 53012 Bonn, Germany

- Completed 78 ECTS credits
- Anticipated graduation date: September 2021

# **Bachelor of Science in Agriculture**

Jun 2010 – Mar 2014

Specialization: Crop Science – Plant Breeding (GPA: 1.63/1.0)

Central Mindanao University, 8710 Musuan, Maramag, Bukidnon, Philippines

• Thesis: "Genetic Diversity and Population Structure of *Oryza rufipogon* Griff. in Lakes Apo and Napalit, Bukidnon"

#### Non-degree Program

Young Southeast Asian Leaders Initiative Institute (YSEALI)

on Global Environmental Issues Maureen and Mike Mansfield Center

University of Montana

59812 Montana, United States of America

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

# **Original Articles**

- Labarosa, S. J., Sevilla, N., Tabanao, D., Baldo, N., Ebuña, H., & Jamago, J. (in press). Genetic Diversity and Structure of Oryza rufipogon Griff. Populations in the Philippines. Philippine Journal of Science, 150 (S1), 17-28.
- Tin, H. Q., Loi, N. H., Labarosa, S. J. E., McNally, K. L., McCouch, S., & Kilian, B. (2020). Phenotypic response of farmer-selected CWR-derived rice lines to salt stress in the Mekong Delta. Crop Science. doi:10.1002/csc2.20354
- Marcelo, V. A. C., Lipio, P. L. G., Labarosa, S. J. E., Mananghaya, T. E., & Niones, J. M. (2020). Assessment of Genetic Diversity and Population Structure of Rice Donor Germplasm Accessions in the Philippines. Philippine Journal of Science, 149(3-a), 685-696.

Labarosa, S.J. Page 1 of 5

Raubach, S., Kilian, B., Dreher, K., Amri, A., Bassi, F.M., Boukar, O., Cook, D., Cruickshank, A., Fatokun, C., El Haddad, N., Humphries, A., Jordan, D., Kehel, Z., Kumar, S., Labarosa, S.J., Nguyen, L.H., Mace, E., McCouch, S., McNally, K., Marshall, D.F., Mikwa, E.O., Milne, I., Odeny, D.A., Plazas, M., Prohens, J., Rieseberg, L.H., Schafleitner, R., Sharma, S., Stephen, G., Tin, H.Q., Togola, A., Warchefsky, E., Werner, P., and Shaw, P.D. (2020). From bits to bites: Advancement of the Germinate platform to support prebreeding informatics for crop wild relatives. Crop Science. doi:10.1002/csc2.20248

#### **Conference Proceedings**

- Labarosa, S. J., Niones, J. M., Balleras, G. D., Espina, J. L. G., Perez, L. M. (2016). Rapid Screening and Identification of New Sources of Field Resistance Genes against Rice Tungro Disease in Philippine Rice Germplasm Materials under PhilRice Midsayap Condition (Abstract). Proceedings of the 46th Annual Scientific Conference.
- **Labarosa, S. J.,** Espina, J. L. G., Niones, J. M. (2016). Yield and its Yield Components Variation among Rainfed Advanced Elite Genotypes in PhilRice Midsayap (Abstract). Proceedings of the 46th Annual Scientific Conference.
- **Labarosa, S. J.**, Tabanao, D. A., and Jamago, J. M. (2015). Genetic Diversity and Population Structure of In Situ Populations of Oryza Rufipogon in Lakes Apo and Napalit, Bukidnon. Transactions of the National Academy of Science and Technology, Vol 37(1), 34.

#### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCES**

Program Officer

Jan 2017 – Aug 2019

Southeast Asia Regional Initiatives for Community Empowerment (SEARICE), Quezon City, Philippines

- Assisted the Executive Director in the core development activities of SEARICE such as community plant genetic resources conservation, management, and sustainable use at the technical and sociological levels.
- Trained several community facilitators and farmers from Lao PDR, Viet Nam, and Myanmar on basic technical knowledge and methodologies on crop improvement using the farmer field school approach.

#### **Science Research Assistant**

Jan 2016 – Dec 2016

Philippine Rice Research Institute (PhilRice)

Central Experiment Station, Nueva Ecija, Philippines

- Assisted in the development of rice advanced breeding lines adapted to soil moisture fluctuations for rainfed and irrigated lowland areas in the Philippines using conventional breeding approach.
- Analyzed the genetic diversity and population structure of several rice parent materials in the crossing block using microsatellite markers to maximize genetic gain potential of F<sub>1</sub> plants and its succeeding line derivatives.

Labarosa, S.J. Page 2 of 5

# Science Research Assistant

Jul 2015 – Dec 2015

Philippine Rice Research Institute (PhilRice)

Midsayap Experiment Station, North Cotabato, Philippines

- Assisted in the yield evaluation of Rainfed Advanced Elite Lines (RAELINES) adapted to soil moisture fluctuations in Mindanao, Philippines.
- Evaluated the different rice germplasm from PhilRice Genebank for rice tungro disease resistance under field condition.

Science Aide Dec 2014 – Jun 2015

College of Forestry and Environmental Science Central Mindanao University,

- Assisted the sound implementation of the DOST-PCAARRD funded project titled
  "Advancement of Science for the Sustainable Utilization and Conservation of Forest
  Genetic Resources of Falcata and Gmelina. Specific functions were the following: o
  assisted in geotagging of Gmelina and Falcata trees in Mindanao; o assisted in the
  generation of map using geographical information of geotagged trees; and
  - o assisted in the collection of Gmelina and Falcata leaf samples for molecular analysis.

# Internships

Science Team Intern Mar – Apr 2020

Global Crop Diversity Trust

Bonn, Germany

Thesis Intern Dec 2013

Philippine Rice Research Institute

Science City of Muñoz, Nueva Ecija, Philippines

Student Intern May 2013

International Rice Research Institute Los Baños, Laguna, Philippines

# AWARDS, GRANTS, and SCHOLARSHIPS RECEIVED

•	Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst (DAAD)	Aug 2019 – Sept 2021
	Scholarship	

•	YSEALI Seeds for the Future Grant Awardee (USD 15,000.00)	Jan 2017
•	YSEALI Generation: EARTH Seed Grant Awardee (USD 1,250.00)	Apr 2015
•	June 2014 Agriculturist Licensure Examination Topnotcher	Jun 2014
	(Ranked 4 <sup>th</sup> out of 5,022 examinees)	

#### **CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS ATTENDED**

# **CSO/NGO** Representative

Nov 2019

8<sup>th</sup> Session of the Governing Body of the International Treaty of Plant Genetic Resources for Food and Agriculture (ITPGRFA)

Rome, Italy

Labarosa, S.J. Page 3 of 5

Participant Sept 2019

Tropentag 2019 Kassel, Germany

Grant Recipient Jan 2017

Young Southeast Asian Leaders Initiative (YSEALI) Seeds for the Future:

Workshop for Grant Recipients

Bangkok, Thailand

#### **Mentor for Environment**

Oct 2016

YSEALI Amplify (Alumni Mentoring Program through Leadership and Influence to Youth) Manila, Philippines

#### **Scientific Poster Presenter**

Sept 2016

28th National Rice R&D Conference

Philippine Rice Research Institute, Science City of Muñoz, Philippines

#### **Scientific Poster Presenter**

Jun 2016

46th Annual Scientific Conference of the Crop Science Society of the Philippines General Santos City, Philippines

#### **Scientific Poster Presenter**

Jul 2015

37th Annual Scientific Meeting, National Academy of Science and Technology Manila, Philippines

# **Philippine Delegate**

Apr 2015

YSEALI Generation: Environmental Advocacy, Responsibility, and Teamwork Workshop Siem Reap, Cambodia

#### **Scientific Poster and Oral Presenter**

Nov 2014

14th National Genetics Symposium, Philippine Society for the Advancement of Genetics, Inc. Iloilo City, Philippines

Participant Nov 2014

BloggedIn: ASEAN – The First ASEAN Blogathon Makati City, Philippines

#### **COMMUNITY-PROJECTS IMPLEMENTED**

# **Co-founder and Project Implementer**

Mar – Apr

2017

EcoMentary Filmmaking and Leadership Workshop, Los Baños, Laguna, Philippines

YouTube channel: https://bit.ly/3f94yyu

Labarosa, S.J. Page 4 of 5

# **Project Implementer**

2016

School Trash Gardening, Sablayan, Occidental Mindoro, Philippines

# **Project Implementer**

May

Jun

2016

ZUMBAligiran: Zumba para sa Kapaligiran (Zumba for the Environment), Manila, Philippines

#### **SKILL**

Proficient in using R for statistical analysis

# **HOBBIES**

- · Play video games, mostly Pokémon
- Landscape and nature photography
- Watching Sci-fi, romantic comedy, and/or musical movies

#### **REFERENCES**

# Joy Membreve Jamago, PhD

Professor 2

Department of Agronomy and Plant Breeding

Central Mindanao University

University Town, 8710 Musuan, Philippines

Email: f.joy.jamago@cmu.edu.ph

# **Benjamin Killian**

Senior Scientist Plant Genetic Resources

Global Crop Diversity Trust

Platz der Vereinten Nationen 7, 53113 Bonn, Germany

Email: benjamin.killian@croptrust.org

#### Prof. Dr. Mathias Becker

**ARTS Course Director** 

Universität Bonn

INRES - Institut für Nutzpflanzenwissenschaften und Ressourcenschutz

Bereich Pflanzenernährung

Karlrobert-Kreiten-Strasse 13, D-53115 Bonn, Germany

Email: mathias.becker@uni-bonn.de

Labarosa, S.J. Page 5 of 5